"The Benefits of Black and Green Teas for Brain Waves"
Tea—whether white tea,
green tea, oolong, or black—
are all made
from the tea plant,
Camellia sinensis.
That's different
from herbal tea,
which is defined
as pouring hot water
over any plant in the world
other than
this particular plant.
There are at least 287,655
different plants
that we know of on this planet.
Why is this one plant
the most popular beverage
in the world?
It's not the caffeine;
the coffee plant
has more caffeine,
but more people drink tea
than coffee.
It's probably not the taste;
most people would
probably prefer peppermint
or some of the fruity
berry teas
to be better tasting.
It's a pretty enough plant,
but why do we drink literally
billions of cups a day
of this particular plant?
It turns out
there's something in this plant
that's found concentrated
in only two places in nature—
in the tea plant
and in an odd mushroom
called the bay bolete,
which has these little holes
instead of gills.
Scientists figured this one
might not pair as well
with crumpets,
so they called the compound
theanine.
What does it do
that's got billions of people
hooked on it?
We weren't quite sure
until we hooked people up
to an EEG.
An electroencephalogram
measures the activity
of our brain waves,
which are split
into four major bandwidths:
we have delta waves,
theta waves,
alpha waves, and beta waves.
Delta waves,
where basically our brain
is electrically pulsing
very slowly
at about a wave per second,
are seen primarily
in deep sleep.
Then there are theta waves—
at about five cycles
per second—
typically seen
when we're drowsy
or in early sleep.
The two waking states
are alpha and beta.
We have alpha brain waves
when we're relaxed,
aware, attentive,
like when we close our eyes
and meditate.
And beta waves are more
when we're stimulated
with increased alertness,
in a hustle-and-bustle state
where most of us
live our lives.
How can we get more
in that alpha state,
that wakeful relaxation,
fully alert and focused
but calm?
Well, if we relax
in a nice peaceful place,
after about 90 minutes
we can start to see
some significant
alpha activity,
which is this yellow and red.
Now, practicing meditators,
like Buddhist monks,
can achieve this state earlier,
and even maintain
alpha activity
with their eyes open.
And the deeper the meditation,
the higher the alpha waves.
So, we can meditate
for 30 years
or just drink some tea.
This was the alpha wave
activity
in the control group
after drinking plain water.
What if, instead of water,
they had the amount of theanine
found in one or two cups
(240 to 480 ml) of tea?
Look closely, compare, and see
if you can detect a difference.
That is why people drink tea
from the tea plant.